Guide to the Rukhl Fishman Papers, 1940-1990
Department of Special Collections
- Series 1. Correspondence, 1940-1984
  - Subseries 2. Incoming correspondence
    - Correspondence in, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      Basman, Rivke; Beker, Yaakov; Bialystotska, P.; Bilitski, Y. Kh.; Birshteyn, Yosl; Birshteyn-Pinar; Bonen, Yitskhok; Codor, Esther; Cohen, Rivke; Fishman, David; Eisenman, Tsvi; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Friedman, Kenya; Frankenshteyn, Carl; Frankenshteyn, Rekhuma; Gai, Asie; Gris, Noyekh; Grosbard, Herts; Gurin, Moyshe; Heifetz-Tussman, Malke; Hofman, Miriam; Karpinovtish, Avrom; Kaspi, Yehudit; Kerler, Yosef; Khup, A.; Korn, Rokhl; Kornhendler, Yekhezkiel; Leftwich, Joseph; Lis, A.; Litvin, Mordkhe; Loyter, L.; Medovnik, Andre; Mikhl, C.L.; Noy, Dov; Osherovitsh, Hirsh; Paneni, Dovid; Paner, Yitskhok; Podriatshik, L.; Ratson, Khave; Rekes, A.; Rock, Stella; Rokhman, Leyb; Roytman, Sholyme; Rozenfeld, Sholem; Ruin, Hadasah; Sadan, Dov; Sfard, David; Shafir, M.M.; Shamir, Bunim; Shedletski, Efrayem; Sherman, B.; Shmeruk, Khone; Shomri, Arye; Shpigelblat, Alexander; Shipgl, Yeshaye; Shtokfish, Dovid; Spiegel, Marcia; Sutzkever, Avrom; Telesin, Ziame; Top, Shmuel; Tsinberg, Eliezer; Verber, Shifre; Waldman, Moyshe; Yanosovitsch, Yitskhok; Zygelbaum, F.; [S.n.] Devora; [S.n.] Shoshana; Hassah Hospital; Hebrew University of Jerusalem; Israeli Broadcasting Network; World Conference in Israel for Yiddish & Jewish Culture; Yisroel-Shtime; Yugutruf
    - Correspondence in, 1977 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      Also contains a copy of Joshua A. Fishman's biography for Who's Who.
      Codor, Esther; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Gershonovitsh, M.; Horowitz, Al; Horowitz, Genia; Horowitz, Martin; Horwitz, Larry; Leuvenburg, J.; Likhtenshteyn, A.; Melamed, Sholem; Podriatshik, Leyzer; Schaecter, Mordkhe; Verpale, Erick; Weiner, Susan; Wolf, Rhonda; Benyumen Shekhter Foundation for the Advancement of Standard Yiddish; I.L. Peretz Publishing Co.; TAL International Publishing: Tel Aviv University
    - Correspondence in, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      Also includes invitations to meeting with members of World Council for Yiddish & Jewish Culture from Office of the President of the State of Israel. Also includes membership card of Rukhl Fishman in the Yiddish P.E.N. Club for 1978-1980.
      Avani, Lina; Avani, Avraham; Bakh, Shloyme; Basman, Rivke; Birshteyn, Yosl; Codor, Esther; Dworkin, Miriam; Fishman, Avi; Eisenman, Tsvi; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Fishman, Sonia; Frankenshteyn, Carl; Gai, Asya; Genosar, Nekhama; Gurin, Moyshe; Hershteyn, Fishl; Hofshteyn, Feyge; Kadari, Tsvi; Kadari, Yehudit; Kahan, Aharon; Karpinovtish, Avrom; Kaspi, Yehudit; Khalomish, Mordkhe; Kiler, Mori; Lehev, Rakhel; Litvin, Mordkhe; Miron, Dan; Ostrovsky, Avi; Patar, Like; Patar, Doni; Preminger, Yitskhok; Ratson, Khave; Rekes, A., Dr.; Ring, Galila; Rivlis, Ezra; Rozenfeld, Sholem; Rubinstein, A.; Sheinman, Claire; Sheinman Family; Shenker, Avraham; Shika, Dov; Shika, Esther; Shiloni, Zahavah; Sivan, Avi; Sutzkever, Avrom; Teitelbaum, Dora; Tickman, Sonia; Turniansky, Khave; Yakir, Ruti; Yungman, Moyshe; Yungman, Miriam; [S.n.], Shoshana Lev; [S.n.], Margalit & Micah; [S.n.], Ilana; [S.n.], Vegtor; [S.n.], Peil [member of Knesset]; Al-Hamishmar; Hadassah Hospital; Hebrew University; Itsik Manger Prize for Literary Work in Yiddish; Knesset; United Labor Party; World Tribune for Yiddish & Yiddish Culture; World Zionist Organization
    - Correspondence in, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      Includes flyer from Aaron Fishman Foundation for Yiddish Culture and booklet from Bat-Mitzvah of Leyele Horwitz.
      Codor, Esther; Cohen, Rafael; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Hershteyn, Fishl; Hofshteyn, Feyge; Horwitz, Leyele; Litvin, Mordkhe; Aaron Fishman Foundation for Yiddish Culture; Society of Yiddish Writers in Israel
    - Correspondence in, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 25)
      Includes Russian-language booklet signed by Evgeny Greiser, and copy of announcement of Sonia Fishman's unveiling.
      Birshteyn, Yosl; Codor, Esther; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Holdheim, Aliza; Litvin, Mordkhe; Younin, Wolf
    - Correspondence in, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 26)
      Includes copy of a letter from Abraham J. Tannenbaum to Theodore Holdheim. Also contains copy of memorial advertisement for Sonia Fishman's yortsayt.
      Codor, Esther; Fishman, Avi; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Heifetz-Tussman, Malke; Holdheim, Theodore; Levitan, Seymour; Litvin, Mordkhe; Tannenbaum, Abraham; Younin, Wolf
    - Correspondence in, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 27)
      Codor, Esther; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Yungman, Moyshe; [S.n.], David
    - Correspondence in, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 27)
      Codor, Esther; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.
    - Correspondence in, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 27)
      Aharoni, Arye; Aharoni, Rakhel; Cohen, Ron; Fishman, Avi; Fishman, Gella Schweid; Fishman, Joshua A.; Heifetz-Tussman, Malke; [S.n.], Mikhal
    - Correspondence in, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 28)
      Codor, Esther; Fishman, Aaron; Fishman, Joshua A.; Fishman, Sonia; Sutzkever, Avrom
    - Correspondence in, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 29)
      Aharoni, Ayre; Heifetz-Tusman, Malke; Eisenman, Tsvi; Goldberg, Sonia; Gorin, Miriam; Gorin, Natan; Grosbard, Herts; Grosbard, Moli; Hofshteyn, Feyge; Horwitz, Martin; Litvin, Mordkhe; Mintz, Ruth Finer; Ockman, Kalman; Shamir, Mia; Sharon, Nakhum; Shomri, Arye; Sofri, Beni; Yaffa, Meyer; [S.n.], Mikhal; [S.n.], Naomi; [S.n.], Rakhel; [S.n.], Saki; [S.n.],; Yisroel-Bukh Publishing House; Camp Boiberik
  - Subseries 3. Other family members
    - Kh. Pupko (D. Tsukunft) to Aaron Fishman re: publication of Rukhl Fishman's poetry, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - A. Verber to Sonia Fishman and Aaron Fishman, 1961 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Aliza Holdheim (mother-in-law of Rukhl Fishman) to Joshua A. Fishman and Gella Schweid Fishman, 1961 - 1979 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Sonia Fishman to Aliza Holdheim, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Joshua A. Fishman to Aliza Holdheim, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Regina Weinreich to Sonia Fishman and Aaron Fishman, 1952, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Martin Horwitz (Sonia Fishman's nephew) to Sonia Fishman, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Malke Heifetz-Tussman to Sonia Fishman and Aaron Fishman, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      Include copy of a poem by Rukhl Fishman
    - Letters of condolence to Joshua A. Fishman and Gella Schweid Fishman upon Rukhl Fishman's death, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Letters of condolence to Theodor Holdheim upon Rukhl Fishman's death, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Subseries 4. Miscellaneous
    - Letter from Yitskhok [Shor?] to ShimonVayntraub, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence of Avrom Sutzkever to Kibbutz Committee and to Mordkhe Schaechter regarding Rukhl Fishman's poetry, 1970 - 1971 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence regarding Rukhl Fishman's Book Committee, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Letter from Zuni Zelitch to Yehude & Galya Zelitch regarding reception for Rukhl Fishman, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Letters from members of the Book Committee, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 34)
      Bez, Kh. Bialostotzky, B.J.; Codor, Esther; Glatshteyn, Yankev; Gutman, Saul; Glanz-Leyeles, Aron; Goldber, Chaim Grade; Heifetz-Tussman, Malke; Hershteyn, Fishl; Hochberg, Shloyme; Kazdan, Ch. S.; Lehrer, Lipe; Mlotek, Joseph; Molodowsky, Kadya; Nevelstein, Roze; Pat, Yankev; Schaecter, Mordkhe; Segal, Louis; Shapiro, Shmuel; Singer, S.D.; Weinreich, Max; Weinreich, Uriel
- Series 2. Poetry manuscripts
  - A pale short line = a bleykh shurele (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Superstitions touch my heart = abergleybns tapn niikh baym hartsn (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - A whole heart = a gants harts (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - A danger = a gefar (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - A great hunger = a groyser hunger (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - A lightening bolt of words = a vort blits (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - If one wants to, one is silent = oyb eyner vii, shvaygt er (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - If from gathering silent sunny grapes= oyb fun kiaybrt shtume zunike troybn (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - If being silent means forgetting = oyb shvaygn heyst fargesn (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - You need a reason for tears = af trern darf men dokh a sibe ol (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oh my grey end-of summer orchard! = oy sof-zumerdiker sod mayner! (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Everywhere = umetum (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Restless, nervous, beautiful! = uznruyik, nervez, sheyn (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - And a too early spring = un a tsu-friyer filing (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - And once again the grapevine is blooming, father ! = un vider blit der vaynsh~ok tate! (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - And once again between us = tin vider tsvishn undz (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Under the armpit = unter der pakhve (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Since you're glowing now = az gust shoyn itst (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Since you don't allow = az du lozst nit (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - So I stood each = azoy bin ikh geshtanen (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - So green, so agile, so light = azoy grii~ azoy flink, azoy laykht (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Like you kitten = azoy vi du ketsl (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - I want to fall like this = a.zoy vii ikh fain (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Such pockets = azelkhe keshenes (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - You are mine = eygn bistu mir (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - My own insanities = eygene meshugasn (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Before I go to see you = eyder ikh gey dir zen (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - One shoulder slightly higher = eyn aksl etvos hekher (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I can fall asleep by myself = aynshlofn ken ikh aleyn (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I am a sheep = ikh a sheps (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I am a great beginner = ikh bin a groyser onfanger (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I am sunned through = ikh bin durkhgezunt (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I bind a rope around me = ikh bind tsu zilch tsu a shtrik (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - I can count on you = ikh bin zikher mit dir (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I am tired = 11th bin mid (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I am not older than I am = ikh bin nit elter vi ikh bin (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I am not lazy = ikh bin nit foyl (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I am full = ikh bin flu (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I left home early = ikh bin fri avek fun hoyz (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I hold your letter = ikh halt dayn briv (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I can wait = ikh ken vattrr (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I know = ikh veys (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - I want so much to sleep = ikh vii azoy shlofn (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - I don't want by myseif = ikh vii nit aleyn (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I look for your poem = ikh zukh dayn lid (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I'm laughing again = ikhiakh shoyn vider (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I don't run anymore = ikhloyf shoyn nit (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I doubt = ikhtsveyfl (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I know a little boy = ikhkon a kleyntshik yingele (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I come so cheerfully in the morning = ikhkum azoy munter in der fri (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I observe = ikhkuk zikh tsu (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I can wait = ikhken vartn (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - A jump up to the rainbow = a shprung tsum regn-boygn (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I can't say it = ikh kenesnitzogn (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I surround myself with books = ikhringi zikh arum mit bikher (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I drag my feet = ikhshiep mayne fis (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - I stand before you = ikh shtey far dir (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - I sharpen my pencil = ikh shnits mayn blayer (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Now I'm afraid = ikh shrek zikh itst (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - I don't fear punishment = ikh shrek zikh nit far shtrof (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - It's a small step = iz a katsn shprung (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - In a hot afternoon = in a heysn baytog (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - In the evening = in ovnt (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - In such a soft night = in aza veykher nakht (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - In such a rain = in aza regn (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - In the beginning = in onheyb (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - In the blue nights = in di bloye nekht (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - In the brightest moments = in di helste minutn (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - In the young orchard = in yungn sod (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - In the round glass bowl of the world = in kaylekhdikn, glezernem veltkrug (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Now is not the time for words = itst iz nit keyn tsayt far verter (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Now you are quieter = itst bistu shtiler (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - You are happy with despair = ir zayt mit yiyesh gliklekh (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Alone in the room = aleyn in tsimer (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - All glances = ale blikn (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Sometimes I think = a mol ikh trakht (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Sometimes at night = a mol in der nakht (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - An ant = a murashke (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - No joking = on a shpas (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - I put on my glasses = ongeton di brim (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Without that = on dem (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Often while writing = oft baym shraybn (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Even a doud = afile a volkn (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - An impertinent fly = a frekhe flig (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - A gentleness = a tsart (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - A cat may look at the king = a kats meg kukn afn kenig (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - A red dot on the wall = a royt pintele af der vant (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Pulling up = aruftsiyen (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Like a smile it blossomed through = arayngeblimit hot zikh vi a shmeykhi (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Dawns = baginens (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Barefoot at night = borves bay nakht (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Until 11 o'dock = biz elf azeyger (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Up to the window = biz tsum fentster (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Bitter = biter (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Spring has come to us = bay undz der filing (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Near the eternal partition = bay der eybiker mekhitse (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Right at the door = bay der tir shoyn (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - For me = bay mir (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - In my heart = bay mir in hartsn (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - At the foot of the tree = baym fus fun boym (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - You ran after me up to the corner = bist biz tsum rog (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - You are already big = bist shoyn groys (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Little blue flames = bloye fayerlekh (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Don't thunder = blits nit (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Better this way = beser azoy (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - I grumbled in anger = broygez a burtshe geton' (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - All or nothing = gor - oder gorrtit (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - It's good to go against the wind = gut geyn kegn vint (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - It's good that there's a mountain here = gut vos do is do a barg (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - O.K., but not about snow = gut, nit vegn shney (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Good books = gute bikher (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - One writes good poems until = gute lider shraybt men biz (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - 11 o'clock = 11 azeyger (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Admit = (Box 8, Folder 24)
    gib tsu
  - Go figure out why = gey veys farvos (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Froglike thoughts in the dark = 25. gedanken zshabes in der flntster (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Something thick = gedikhts (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - I really thought = gemeynt hob ikh gemeynt (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - I came too early = gekumen tsu fri (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Wide-eyed = groys oygik (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Here in a far corner = 26. do in vinkl-ek (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Here at the foot of the tree = do baym fus fun boym (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - The colt kicks in the field = dos loshild briket in feld (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - The spoonful of memory = dos lefele zikorn (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - This time = dos mol (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - I cannot understand this = dos ken ikh nit farshteyn (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - You know of course = du veyst dokh (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Just when I ride = 27. davke yen ikh rayt (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - The embers = di haleveshkes (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - The sun is cozy = di zun zi is gemitiekh (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Your longing wakes me up = dayn benken vekt mikh uf (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Your fear, your loneliness = dayn shrek, dayn elnt (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - The moon rises from the east = di levone heybt zilch uf fun (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - The nights don't let me sleep = di nekht iozn nit shlofn (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - My fingers outstretched = di finger oysgetsoygn (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - You are fortunate = dir iz voyl (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - I can tell you this = dir ken ikh dos zogn (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - The whole way back = dem gantsn veg tsurik (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - The sky lays spread out = 29. der himi ligt an oysgeshpreyter (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - The old man woke up shivering = der zokn iz ufgeshtanen fartsitert (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - The boy on the top floor = der yingl fun eybershtn shtok (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - The lightening-force of a poem = der mu.z blits fun lid (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Three that are four = dray vos zaynen fir (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Three shadows = dray shotns (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Half words = halbe verter (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Sweet as honey = honik zis (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - You have good teachers = host gute lerer (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Did you receive my letter? = hostu mayn briv bakumen? (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - You have cold ears = host kalte oyern (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Hollow = hoyl (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Lift yourself out from the truth = heyb zikh aroys fun emes (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Lift yourself out of yourself = heyb zikh aroys fun zikh (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Do pick me up = heyb mikh yo oyf! (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Hoarse birds = heyzerike feygl (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Heaven among the grass = himi tsvishn grozn (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Today there are douds again = haynt iz shoyn vider volkn (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Hot honey = heyser honik (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Were we each to the other = voltn mir zikh eynem dem andern (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Clouds = volkn (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - What's the matter? = vos iz? (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - What bothers you? = vos iz dir? (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The thicker it is = vos gedikhter (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Whatdoldo = vostuikh (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Again I returned to the word = vider ongekumen tsum vort (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Again - the large yellow animal = vider - di groyse gele khaye (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Lost again = vider farblondzshet (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Like heart-pangs = vi harts - idep (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - How wild = vi vild (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Woe = vey (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - It seems = vayzt oys (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - I don't know what to do = veys ikh nt vos tsu ton (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - White clouds in the night = vayse volkns in der nakht (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Like a tall glass of milk = vi milkh a hoykhe gloz (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Don't go away like the wind = vint nit avek (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - How many voices does the night 6. vifi koyles hot di nakht have (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Wrap me and draw me close = vild farviki un tulye mir ayn (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Wipe the words from your lips = vish op di lipn (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - If I had a little more nerve = yen ikh hob a bisele mer khutspe (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - If you could catch me = yen du kenst mikh khapn (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - If I were = yen kh'volt geven (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - When my hair is wet = yen mayne hor zaynen nas (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - If someone would = yen s'volt emets (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Wake me up in the middle of the night = vek mikh uf in mitn der nakht (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Who should understand what = ver darf vos farshteyn (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Who opened the closed shutters? = ver hot di farmakhte iodns ufgemakht? (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - You become green as you gallop = verst grin un galop (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - You should always try (1) = zoist zikh tomed miyen (1) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - You should always try (2) = zoist zikh tomed miyen (2) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - You should wake me = zolst mikh vekn (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Juicy = zaftik (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Seventh beggar, finish the story = zibeter betler, farendik di mayse (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - She grates = zi griltst (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Forgive me = zay mir moykhl (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - To be = zayn (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Sure of myself = zikher mit zikh (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Sunny green days = zunik grine teg (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - We said good-bye = zilch gezegnt (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Silver steel against the sun = zilber shtol antkegn zun (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Really = take (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Foolish rabbit = tamavater hoz (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Dear little tiger = tayerer tigerl (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Days and nights = teg un nekht (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Yes = yo (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Embrace me like the sea = yam mikh arum (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Although = khotsh (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Grab the laughing jug = khap on dem lakhndikn krug (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Don't exaggerate = khap nit iber (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - I once = kh'hob eyn mol (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - I saw = kh'hob gezen (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - I thought I could wait = kh'hob gemeynt ikh ken vartn (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - I wandered around = kh'hob zikh arumgedreyt (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - I realized = kh'hob zikh gekhapt (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - I glanced at your hand = 11. kh'hob zikh farkukt af dayn hant (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Fve already said it = kh'hob es shoyn gezogt (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - I have time = kh'hob tsayt (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - I've never = kh'hob keyn mol (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - I won't disturb your wakeful sleep kh'vel dayn vakhn shiof nit shtern (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - I will hide myself in the cold = kh'vel zikh bahaltn in snigoyen (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - madness = in kaltn (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - I carry on my shoulders = kh'trog af mayne pleytses (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - I drink too much coffee = kh'trink tsu fil kave (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - I run = kh'loyf (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - I speak less and less = kh'red ails veyniker un veyniker (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Leave a dean table after yourself = loz nokh zikh a reynem fish (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Let's put on the table = 13. lomir shteln afn fish (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Clear = loyter (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Clear, light, scrubbed dean = loyter, gring, oysgetsvogn (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - You will still write poems = lider vestu nokh farshraybn (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Poems for my birthday = lider far mayn geburtstog (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Mama, I can't fall asleep = mame ikh ken nit aynshlofn (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Lucky rabbit = mazldikher hoz (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Written with a pencil = mit a blayer geshribn (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - With a bark = mit a gebil (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - With the awesome courage = mit der geferlekher mut (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - With stony stones = mit shteynerne shteyner (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - The field is sown with stones = mit shteyner farzeyt dos feld (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - With a strict hand = mit shtrertger hant (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - My corner of pain = 16. mayn vinkl vey (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - My blood still neighs = mayne blutn hirzshen alts (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - My dreams chew grass = mayne khaloymes kayen groz (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - My poems = mayne lider (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - My pulses and impulses = 18. mayne pulsn un impulsn (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - My happiness is no longer yours = mayn freyd iz shoyn mer nit dayne (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Mister Van Gough! = mister van-gokh! (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - The two of us = mir beyde (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Today we = mir hobn zikh haynt (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - We look at the sea = mir kukn am yam (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - We hammer and hammer = mir shmidn un shmidn (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Sometimes you can be impertinent = m'meg a mol zayn frekh (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - With children you should = men zol mit kinder (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Days and nights = mes-lesn (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - After such a winter = 20. nokh aza vinter (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Before I put forth my first words = nokh eyder kh'hob geshtelt di ershte verter (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - After the summer = nokhn zumer (Box 9, Folder 21)